Guide to the Langston Hughes Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Langston Hughes collection
1924-1969
JWJ MSS 28
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.75
(4 boxes) + 1 art storage item
The Langston Hughes Collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, sound recordings, video recordings, electronic files, and other material documenting the life, work, and remembrance of Langston Hughes. Series I, Josephine DeWitt Rhodehamel Gift, is organized into three subseries: Letters from Langston Hughes, Writings of Langston Hughes and Writings of Others. There are letters to Rhodehamel and holograph and typescript versions of poems for Dear Lovely Death. Series II, Material from Other Sources, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Photographs, Audiovisual Materials, and Electronic Files. There are groups of letters to Arna Bontemps, Harold Jackman, Arthur Spingarn, Nathaniel White and others. Audiovisual material consists of commercial recordings of Langston Hughes's work, as well as video recordings of two sessions from Yale University's "Langston Hughes and His World" conference in February 2002. Electronic files include preliminary and final versions of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library's online exhibition, "Langston Hughes at 100."
Other Storage Formats: Audio Recordings, Video Recordings, Electronic Files, 1 art storage item
Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Langston Hughes Collection was acquired through various gifts and purchases to complement the Langston Hughes Papers (JWJ MSS 26). Audiovisual materials and electronic files were acquired or produced at the time of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscipt Library's Hughes centenary exhibition and conference in 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 4: Folders 30 and 34 are unused. Original recordings are in Box 2, folders 38 and 39.
LANGSTON HUGHES (1902-1967)
A biographical timeline is provided in the Langston Hughes Papers (JWJ MSS 26).
Scope and Contents
The Langston Hughes Collection consists of letters, manuscripts, audiovisual recordings and other material documenting the life, work, and remembrance of Langston Hughes. The collection spans the years 1924-2002.
The collection is housed in 4 boxes and organized into two series: Josephine DeWitt Rhodehamel Gift and Material from Other Sources. Box 2 contains material that is Restricted Fragile.
Series I, Josephine DeWitt Rhodehamel Gift, is organized into three subseries: Letters from Langston Hughes, Writings of Langston Hughes and Writings of Others. Letters from Langston Hughes, housed in box 1, consist exclusively of letters from Hughes to Rhodehamel, of Berkeley, California, dating from 1930-40. Letters mention Rhodehamel's efforts to acquire particular pieces of work by Hughes for herself and "the library," his work and travel, and his gratitude for her interest. The Writings of Langston Hughes subseries contains holograph and typescript versions of poems for Dear Lovely Death (1931) laid in decorated boards. There is also a typescript copy of Louise Thompson's article on Hughes' first novel, Not Without Laughter (1930).
Series II, Material from Other Sources, housed in boxes 1, 3, and 4, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Photographs, Audiovisual Material and Electronic Files. The Correspondence subseries consists of correspondence from Hughes to others and is arranged alphabetically by recipient. There are groups of letters to Arna Bontemps, Harold Jackman, Arthur Spingarn, Nathaniel White and others. More than 20 letters to Arna Bontemps, dating from March to September 1948, deal with their anthology The Poetry of the Negro (1949). Most of Hughes' letters to Harold Jackman are brief, but longer letters from 1924 and 1933 respectively touch on the economic hardships of life in Paris and the production of Hughes' plays, "Mulatto" and "The Ways of White Folks," by the Harlem Experimental Theatre. Hughes solicited Arthur Spingarn's help in early December 1935 to obtain royalties from the American Play Company for the Vanderbilt Theatre's production of "Mulatto," and subsequent letters, also dating from December 1935, discuss Spingarn's efforts on his behalf. There are many brief letters and cards to Nathaniel White, one of Hughes' assistants, dating from the late 1940s to early 1950s. Enclosures, third-party correspondence and correspondence to Hughes are noted in the folder description. There are photographs of Hughes dating from 1934 and 1969.
The Audiovisual Material subseries consists of audio and video recordings acquired or produced by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library for the Library's 2002 exhibition "Langston at 100" and the Yale University conference "Langston Hughes and His World" which was held by the University's Department of African American Studies and the Beinecke Library in February 2002. The material includes both commercial recordings relating to Hughes, and video recordings of "Langston Hughes and His World" conference sessions "An Evening of Jazz and Poetry" and "The Theatre of Langston Hughes." The Electronic Files subseries consists of preliminary and final .html files for the online exhibition "Langston Hughes at 100."
Restricted Fragile materials are housed in box 2.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Harlem Renaissance -- Archives; Born digital; Compact discs; Photographic prints; Videocassettes; Authors; Poets; Bontemps, Arna, 1902-1973; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Jackman, Harold, 1901-1961; Rhodehamel, Josephine DeWitt; Spingarn, Arthur B. (Arthur Barnett), 1878-1971; White, Nathaniel; Yale University. Dept. of African American Studies; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; Langston Hughes and His World -- New Haven, Conn. -- 2002; Langston Hughes at 100 (Exhibition: New Haven, CT) -- 2002
- Josephine DeWitt Rhodehamel Gift, 1930-1940; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Josephine DeWitt Rhodehamel, 1964
  - LETTERS FROM LANGSTON HUGHES
    - Correspondence, 1930-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes clipping of poems in Russian and printed advertisement for the 1936 Curran Theatre production of "Mulatto"
  - WRITINGS OF LANGSTON HUGHES
    - "Dear Lovely Death," poems, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - "Langston Hughes, Novelist," article by Louise Thompson, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Material from Other Sources, 1924-2002; Series II; 1.33; (2 boxes)
  Correspondence and Photographs acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Audiovisual Material and Electronic Files acquired or produced by the Beinecke Library for the Hughes centenary exhibition and conference in 2002.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bontemps, Arna, 1948-64, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes letter from Bontemps to Hughes
    - Franklin, "Miss", 1927 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Friedberg, Leavia, 1942, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes printed invitations and letters to Hughes from Josh White and the Negro Actors Guild of America
    - Gallop, Donald, 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hill, Lawrence, 1963 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Contains copy of letter
    - Jackman, Harold, 1924-37 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes review of Gilpin Players 1936 production of "Little Ham" at the Karamu Theater
    - Rutherford, Tom, 1942 Sep (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes letter from Rutherford to Bernard Knollenberg
    - Spingarn, Arthur B. (Arthur Barnett), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - White, Nathaniel, 1946-51, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes postcard from White to Hughes
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Photograph of Langston Hughes, 1969 Jul (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photograph of Langston Hughes by Sibyl Anikeeff, [1934 Sep 15?] (Box Art, Folder 14)
  - AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
    - Commercial Sound Recordings
      - Black nativity - gospel on Broadway [Compact disc], 2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        Re-release of VeeJay 5022 (1962)
        Collectables, COL-CD-7161
      - Amaize, Odekhiren. The Negro speaks of rivers, and other art songs by African- American composers [Compact disc], 1999 (Box 3, Folder 18)
        Musician Showcase Recordings, MS1011
      - Jimmie Lunceford and his orchestra, 1941-1945 (French import) [Compact disc], 1996 (Box 3, Folder 19)
        Classics 862
      - Lincoln, Abbey. Abbey is blue (Japanese import) [Compact disc], 2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        VICJ-60490
      - Lincoln, Abbey. Straight ahead [Compact disc], 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
        Candid, CCD 79015
      - Lutcher, Nellie. The Best of Nellie Lutcher [Compact disc], 1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
        Capitol Jazz, CDP 7243 8 35039 2 6
      - Midge Williams and her Jazz Jesters, 1937-1938 (French import) [Compact disc], 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        Classics 745
      - Siegmeister, Elie. Selections [Compact disc], 1999 (Box 3, Folder 24)
        CRI American masters series, CRI 814
      - Weary blues with Langston Hughes, Charles Mingus, and Leonard Feather [Compact disc], 1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
        Verve 841 660-2
    - Commercial Videocassettes, These videocassettes are commercial and have not been digitized.
      - Black Americans of Achievement Video Collection II, Langston Hughes (1994) [VHS] (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Looking for Langston (1989) [VHS], 1992 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Stormy Weather (1943) [VHS], 1991 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Media Produced by and for Beinecke Events
      Conditions Governing Access
      Box 2: Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Langston Hughes at 100, 2002 Feb 1; 1; This is a videocassette copy of the original recording. It has not been digitized. (Box 4, Folder 29, Item barcode 39002104618237)
        Accompanied by program
      - "An Evening of Jazz and Poetry," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centenniel Celebration conference, Yale University (Tape 1 of 2), 2002 Feb 22; 1 (Box 2, Folder 38, Item barcode 39002104618302)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - "An Evening of Jazz and Poetry," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centenniel Celebration conference, Yale University (Tape 2 of 2), 2002 Feb 22; 1 (Box 2, Folder 38, Item barcode 39002104618310)
      - "An Evening of Jazz and Poetry," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centenniel Celebration conference, Yale University (1 of 2), 2002 Feb 22; 1; This is a videocassette copy of the original recording. It has not been digitized. (Box 4, Folder 31, Item barcode 39002104618245)
      - "An Evening of Jazz and Poetry," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centenniel Celebration conference, Yale University (2 of 2), 2002 Feb 22; 1; This is a videocassette copy of the original recording. It has not been digitized. (Box 4, Folder 32, Item barcode 39002104618252)
      - "The Theatre of Langston Hughes," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centennial Celebration conference, Yale University (Tape 1 of 2), 2002 Feb 23; 1 (Box 2, Folder 39, Item barcode 39002104618328)
      - "The Theatre of Langston Hughes," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centennial Celebration conference, Yale University (Tape 2 of 2), 2002 Feb 23; 1 (Box 2, Folder 39, Item barcode 39002104618336)
      - "The Theatre of Langston Hughes," Langston Hughes and His World: A Centennial Celebration conference, Yale University [VHS], 2002 Feb 23; This is a videocassette copy of the original recording. It has not been digitized. (Box 4, Folder 34, Item barcode 39002104618294)
      - Langston Hughes Reads - CD format [Compact disc], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - ELECTRONIC FILES
    - "Langston at 100" website, .html files, preliminary version, [2002] (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Langston at 100" website, .html files, final version ("Web and library versions"), 2002 Jan 30 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.21; (1 box)
  Box 2: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Box 1, folder 12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Box 4, folder 33 (Box 2, Folder 39)